<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><typeSystemDescription xmlns="http://uima.apache.org/resourceSpecifier">
  <name>TemporalExpression</name>
  <description>The temporal expression types are needed for event models, and they are used in event-based EDAs.
This file defines two set of types: One is TemporalExpression and the other is DefaultTimeOfText and its subtypes. TemporalExpression has four sub-types: Date, Time, Duration, and Set.</description>
  <version>1.0</version>
  <vendor/>
  <types>
    <typeDescription>
      <name>eu.excitement.type.temporal.DefaultTimeOfText</name>
      <description>It is anchored to a textual region (a paragraph, or a document), and holds the "default time" that has been determined for this passage and can be useful to interpret relative time expressions ("now", "yesterday") in the text.</description>
      <supertypeName>uima.tcas.Annotation</supertypeName>
      <features>
        <featureDescription>
          <name>time</name>
          <description>This feature holds the default time for the textual unit which is annotated
by this annotation. The time string is expressed in the normalized ISO 8601 format. More specifically,
it is a concatenation of the ISO 8601 calendar date and extended time: "YYYY-MM-DD hh:mm:ss".</description>
          <rangeTypeName>uima.cas.String</rangeTypeName>
        </featureDescription>
      </features>
    </typeDescription>
    <typeDescription>
      <name>eu.excitement.type.temporal.TemporalExpression</name>
      <description>TemporalExpression annotates a temporal expression. It is a uima.tcas.Annotation that annotates a temporal expression within a passage, adding a normalized time representation. It holds two string features: One contains the original temporal expression, and the other contains a normalized time representation, using ISO 8601. This is the top annotation for temporal expressions, with a normalized time representation. It has four subtypes, which reflects TIMEX3 temporal types of Date, Time, Duration and Set</description>
      <supertypeName>uima.tcas.Annotation</supertypeName>
      <features>
        <featureDescription>
          <name>text</name>
          <description>his feature holds the original expression appearing in the text.</description>
          <rangeTypeName>uima.cas.String</rangeTypeName>
        </featureDescription>
        <featureDescription>
          <name>resolvedTime</name>
          <description>This feature holds the resolved time in ISO 8601 format. For
example, "Yesterday", will be resolved into "2012-11-01", etc. See the type DefaultTimeOfText for details.</description>
          <rangeTypeName>uima.cas.String</rangeTypeName>
        </featureDescription>
      </features>
    </typeDescription>
    <typeDescription>
      <name>eu.excitement.type.temporal.Date</name>
      <description>This type represents a temporal expression of type Date. The expression describes a calendar time like yesterday, November 1943, Tuesday 18th, etc.</description>
      <supertypeName>eu.excitement.type.temporal.TemporalExpression</supertypeName>
    </typeDescription>
    <typeDescription>
      <name>eu.excitement.type.temporal.Time</name>
      <description>This type represents a temporal expression of type Time. The expression refers to a time of the day, even if in a very indefinite way: eleven in the morning, late last night, twenty
after twelve, etc.</description>
      <supertypeName>eu.excitement.type.temporal.TemporalExpression</supertypeName>
    </typeDescription>
    <typeDescription>
      <name>eu.excitement.type.temporal.Duration</name>
      <description>This type represents a temporal expression of type Duration. The expression describes a duration with explicit durations: 2 months, 48 hours, all last night, 20 days, etc.</description>
      <supertypeName>eu.excitement.type.temporal.TemporalExpression</supertypeName>
    </typeDescription>
    <typeDescription>
      <name>eu.excitement.type.temporal.Set</name>
      <description>This type represents a temporal expression of type Set. For example, every winter,
each Monday, etc. It indicates a recurrence pattern.</description>
      <supertypeName>eu.excitement.type.temporal.TemporalExpression</supertypeName>
    </typeDescription>
  </types>
</typeSystemDescription>
